John W. Ryan papers, 1950-2011 C458
Indiana University Archives
John W. Ryan papers
1950-2011
1950-1993
Indiana University Archives
Ryan, John W. (John William), 1929-2011
C458
18.8 cubic feet 20 boxes
John W. Ryan served as the fourteenth president of Indiana University from 1971-1987. During this time, he was awarded many honors, including honorary degrees, and was active in many organizations. These organizations include the Air Force's Air University, American Society for Public Administration, Indiana Bell Telephone Company, College of St. Thomas, and State Life Insurance Company. These papers include records regarding his membership in various organizations outside and apart from IU, teaching files, speeches as well as correspondence and other personal files.
Access Restrictions
Select files closed to researchers. Advance notice required for access to collection.
Biographical Note
John William Ryan was born on August 12, 1929, in Chicago, Illinois. He earned his Bachelor of Arts degree at the University of Utah in 1951 and earned his master's degree and Ph.D. at Indiana University in 1958 and 1959, respectively. He was a research analyst in the Department of Revenue for the Commonwealth of Kentucky, 1953-55; research associate in the I.U. Program in Public Administration in Thailand, 1955-57; Assistant Director of the Institute of Training for Public Service on the Bloomington Campus, 1957-58; Associate Director, Bureau of Government, University of Wisconsin, 1958-62; Executive Assistant to the President and University Secretary, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, 1962-63; Vice- President for Academic Affairs, Arizona State University, 1963-65; and Chancellor, University of Massachusetts, Boston, 1965-68.
In July 1968, he became Vice-President and Chancellor for Regional Campuses at Indiana University. In this post he guided the development of the campuses at Fort Wayne, South Bend, Gary (Northwest), Kokomo, and Jeffersonville (Southeast) from extension centers to degree-granting divisions. On January 26, 1971, Ryan was elected the 14th president of Indiana University. As President, he saw the establishment of two new IU campuses in New Albany (Indiana University Southeast) and in Richmond (Indiana University East). He also oversaw the formation of various cultural centers on the IU Bloomington campus and the creation of the IU School of Journalism, IU School of Continuing Studies, the IU School of Optometry, and the IU School of Public and Environmental Affairs. During this time, he was also active in many organizations including the Air Force's Air University, American Society for Public Administration, Indiana Bell Telephone Company, College of St. Thomas, and State Life Insurance Company.
In 1987, Dr. Ryan retired as president and was awarded the title President Emeritus of Indiana University. He continued to serve as a professor in the School of Public and Environmental Affairs and as a member of several boards and committees. Ryan also maintained an active public role as a liaison, public speaker, and representative for IU. He also served in short-term administrative roles including as interim president at the University of Maryland at Baltimore and at Florida Atlantic University, as advisor to the Papua New Guinea Commission for Higher Education, and as Chancellor of the State University of New York.
In 1949, he married D. Patricia Goodday. They had three children, Kathleen Elynne, born in 1950; Kevin Dennis Mitchell, in 1951; and Kerrick Charles Casey, in 1953. Dr. Ryan died on August 6, 2011.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: Organizations, Speeches, Course and Research files and Letters and personal files. Records in the first series are then divided into seven different sub-series: Agency for International Development, Air University Board of Visitors, American Society for Public Administration (ASPA), Indiana Bell Telephone Company, College of St. Thomas Board of Trustees, State Life Insurance Company and General. The Couse and Research Files series is also further divided into three separate series: Indiana University, University of Wisconsin and Arizona State and University of Massachusetts.
Scope and Content Note
This collection is arranged into four series: Organizations, Speeches files, Course and Research Files and Letters and personal files. All records were retained in the original order that they were received.
The Organizations series (1961-1993) is further organized into seven sub-series.
The first sub-series, Agency for International Development (1991-1993) contains records from John Ryan's tenure as the Senior Counsel to the Administrator for Management Training in Central and Eastern Europe. Records include related correspondence, reports and project proposals.
The second, Air University Board of Visitors (1974-1981), contains records primarily drawn from John Ryan's tenure as Chairman on the Air Force Institute of Technology Subcommittee from 1976-1981. It consists of meetings minutes, reports, publications and notes relating to program evaluation, curriculum development, personnel changes and accreditation.
The largest sub-series consists of American Society for Public Administration (ASPA) files (1961-1983) and contains records from Ryan's tenure as a member and President of the organization It includes committee and task force files, meeting and conference materials, program proposals and survey data, correspondence files.
The next largest sub-series consists of records relating to Ryan's tenure on the Indiana Bell Telephone Company Board of Directors (1973-1984), and includes meeting and committee materials and correspondence files.
The next two sub-series cover his tenure on the College of St. Thomas Board of Trustees (1972-1984) and on the Board of Directors for the State Life Insurance Company (1977-1985).
The General sub-series (1972-1986) consists of files relating to several other of Ryan's affiliations with which he was involved on a much smaller scale, such as the American Fletcher National Bank (AFNB), Corporate Community Council, Indiana Society for Public Administration (ISPA), National Academy of Public Administrators (NAPA), National Institution of Public Management.
The Speeches series (1958-1968) consist primarily of those speeches Ryan gave during his tenure as Vice President of Academic Affairs at Arizona State University from 1963-1965 and as Chancellor of the University of Massachusetts in Boston from 1965-1968, primarily at faculty and student convocations.
The Couse and Research Files series (1950-1988) consists of research and teaching materials dating primarily from his early career, prior to his appointment as Vice President and Chancellor for Regional Campuses and then President at IU. The series is divided into four separate sub-series which reflect roughly his tenure at 4 separate institutions. The Indiana University sub-series (1950-1988) includes course files documenting Ryan's pursuit of his M.A. and Ph.D. at Indiana University. These files consist primarily of lecture notes and his student papers and exams which are restricted. This sub-series also includes reports and related correspondence from his tenure as a Research Associate from 1955-1957 in an IU program which assisted in establishing the graduate public administration program at the University of Thammsat in Bangkok, Thailand, and as the Assistant Director of the Institute of Training for Public Service from 1957-1958.
The University of Wisconsin sub-series (1955-1963) consists of files from the period when Ryan taught political science and was Associate Director of the Bureau of Government. Files consist mostly of lecture and exam outlines as well as published reports from the Bureau of Government. Similarly, the Arizona State and University of Massachusetts sub-series includes lecture and course materials, as well as some student work.
The final series of Letters and Personal Files (1965-2011) consists primarily of correspondence and includes congratulatory letters upon Ryan's election to the Presidency of Indiana University.
Separated Material
Three unrelated VHS tapes were removed and moved to the film collection. Also removed was a recorder and its accessories.
Some photographs were pulled and transferred to the photograph collection. In these photographs are images of Herman B. Wells and the Indiana University Thai Project of 1955 and 36 images of Joe Sutton.
Related Material
Additional publications and research materials may be accessed in IUScholarworks: http://scholarworks.iu.edu/
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database: http://webapp1.dlib.indiana.edu/archivesphotos/
Acquisition Information
Accession numbers 9026-9032, 0860, 1011, 9033, 9044, 2013/003
Appraisal
Items containing social security numbers were removed and shredded.
College presidents --Indiana --Archives.; Ryan, John W. (John William), 1929-2011 -- Archives; Ryan, John W. (John William), 1929-2011 -- Correspondence; Indiana University. President -- Archives
- Organizations, 1961-1993; undated
  - Agency for International Development (AID), 1991-1993
    - Albania, Hungary and Slovakia Observations Report, 1992 (Box 1)
    - American Council for Education Panel (ACE), 1992 (Box 1)
    - American University of Bulgaria (AUBF), Workings Papers for the Board Committee of Student Affairs, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Czecho-Slovak, Poland, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
      - 1991, (2 folders) (Box 1)
      - 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - Designing U.S. Policy to Accelerate Creation of Market-Based Economics in Central and Eastern Europe, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Human Capital Development Eastern Europe and the Near East, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Materials, 1991-1992; (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - MBA Enterprise, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Meeting w/Dr. Ronald Roskins and others, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1991; (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Network Organizations CDC, 1991 (Box 1)
    - New Venture Development Corporation, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Role, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Romania-Bulgaria (Box 1)
      - General, 1992; (2 folders) (Box 1)
      - Observations, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Special Advisor for Management Training in Central and Eastern Europe, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Survey Data (unidentified), 1992 (Box 2)
  - Air University, Board of Visitors, Force Institute of Technology, 1974-1981
    - Air Command and Staff College (ACSC) Associate Programs Information, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
    - Air University Board of Directors, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Subcommittee of the Air University Board of Visitors, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Air University (Box 2)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
      - 1977 (Box 2)
    - Board of Visitors, Alabama, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Subcommittee (Box 2)
      - 1977, (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - 1978 (Box 2)
    - Air University, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Wright-Patterson Air Force Base, 1978 (Box 2)
    - General, 1979; (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Air Force, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Report, 1980 (Box 2)
    - General, 1980; (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 2)
  - American Society for Public Administration (ASPA), 1961-1983; undated
    - Committees (Box 2)
      - Ad Hoc Committee of Chapter Presidents, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      - Advisory Committee of Presidents, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Affiliate Committee, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Affirmative Action Programs for Women in Schools of Public Administration (NASPAA-ASPA Committee), 1972 (Box 2)
      - Annual Conference Preparation and Program Committee, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Appointment of Seymour Berlin, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Committee to Select an Executive Director for ASPA, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Committee Appointments, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Committees, undated (Box 3)
      - Constitutional Review Committee, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Executive Committee and Finance Committee, 1971 (Box 3)
      - Executive Committee, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Executive Director, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Executive Director Selection, 1972; emph: RESTRICTED (Box 3)
      - Finance and Administration Committee, 1972 (Box 3)
      - General Committee, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Goals and Implementation Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      - Inner Cities - Urban Administration Committee, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Intergovernmental Personnel act (ASPA Task Force), 1972 (Box 3)
      - International and Development Committee, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Joint Council of Education for Public Management, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Los Angeles Conference Program, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Membership and Chapter Development Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
      - National Council of the Conference of Minority Public Administrators, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Nominating Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      - Program Committee for the 1973 ASPA Conference, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      - Program Planning Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      - Program to Study the Administrative Problems of Health Care in U.S., 1972 (Box 3)
      - Progress Fund Stage II Committee, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and Communications (Box 3)
      - Appreciation Letters Sent, 1973 (Box 3)
      - Appreciation Letters Received, 1973 (Box 3)
      - Charlie's Correspondence (Box 3)
        - General, 1972 (Box 3)
        - Personal, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Chapter Communications (Box 3)
        - A-D, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
        - E-H, 1972 (Box 3)
        - I-L, 1972 (Box 3)
        - M-P, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      - Chapter President's Communication, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
        - 1971 (Box 3)
        - 1976 (Box 3)
        - 1977 (Box 3)
        - 1978 (Box 3)
        - 1979 (Box 3)
        - 1980 (Box 3)
      - General Communication, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
      - General Communications from the National Office ASPA, 1972 (Box 3)
      - General Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 3)
      - M Many, 1972 (Box 3)
      - National Council Members, Communications from, 1972 (Box 3)
      - President's Monthly Chapter Letters, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Standing Committee Correspondence, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Finances (Box 4)
      - Deficit Analysis, 1969-1971 (Box 4)
      - Draft Letter on Finances, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Finance and Administration Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
      - Financial, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Financial Condition, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
      - Financial Planning and Adjustments, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Financial Statements, 1970-1972 (Box 4)
      - Letter on Finances, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Letters Concerning Financial Position of ASPA, 1972 (Box 4)
      - National Council, Philadelphia, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Progress Report, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - General (Box 4)
      - ASPA (Box 4)
        - 1972-1973 (Box 4)
        - 1980-1983 (Box 4)
      - Annual Report, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Awards Nomination Form, etc., 1970-1971 (Box 4)
      - Berlin and Ruckelshouse, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Brademas Materials, 1970 (Box 4)
      - Brochures, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Computer Utilization Account Reports, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
      - Constitution, undated (Box 4)
      - Council Elections, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Directory, 1961 (Box 4)
      - Faculty Union, 1971 (Box 4)
      - General II, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
      - General IV, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
      - Goals Report - Annual Meeting, Discussion Reports, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Grant Garvey Memorial Fund, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Hegis Data Requirements, 1971 (Box 4)
      - History, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
      - Intergovernmental Personnel Act, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
      - Letterhead, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Membership, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
      - Monthly Newsletter, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
      - National, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
      - National Conference, 1976 (Box 4)
      - National Council - Appointments, 1972 (Box 4)
      - News and Views, 1970-1973 (Box 4)
      - New Public Administration, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Nominations, 1975 (Box 4)
      - Nominating Committee, 1975 (Box 4)
      - Opinion Survey Questionnaire Copies, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Participants at ASPA Meetings, Constitutional Revision, 1969 (Box 4)
      - Past ASPA Presidents, List of, 1972 (Box 4)
      - President-Elect ASPA John W. Ryan, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Questionnaire Constitutional Revision, 1969 (Box 4)
      - Questionnaire and Codebook, undated (Box 4)
      - Questionnaire Responses, undated (Box 4)
      - Resignations of Council Members, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Resignation of Executive Director, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Transcripts of ASPA Meetings, Notes on, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Indiana (Box 4)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 4)
      - ASPA Award, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
      - Brademas, John, Indiana ASPA Meeting, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
      - Meetings, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Meetings (Box 4)
      - Boston Meeting, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Central Ohio Chapter Meeting, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Colorado Chapter Meeting, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Conference on Academic-Governmental Interaction in the Face of A Changing Federalism, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Congressional Meeting in Washington, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Council, 1970 (Box 4)
      - Council Meeting, 1969 (Box 5)
      - Council Meeting, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Los Angeles Annual Conference, 1972 (Box 5)
      - Meeting Record, 1970 (Box 5)
      - Miami Conference, 1969 (Box 5)
      - NAPA Meeting, 1970 (Box 5)
      - National Conference, New York, 1972 (Box 5)
      - National Council Meeting, 1973 (Box 5)
      - National Executive Committee Meeting, 1972 (Box 5)
      - ASPA New England Regional Conference, 1970 (Box 5)
      - Omaha, 1972 (Box 5)
      - OMB Conference, 1972 (Box 5)
      - Richmond, Virginia, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Sacramento Materials, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Regions, 1972 (Box 5)
      - Regional Meetings, Region I, 1972 (Box 5)
      - Regional Meetings, Region II, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Selection of 1977 and 1978 Annual Conference Sites, 1972-1973 (Box 5)
      - Syracuse Conference File, 1972 (Box 5)
    - National Association of Schools of Public Affairs and Administration (NASPAA) (Box 5)
      - 1971-1973 (Box 5)
      - "1972" (Box 5)
      - New York, 1972 (Box 5)
    - National Academy of Public Administration (NAPA) (Box 5)
      - 1970-1973 (Box 5)
      - "1972-1973" (Box 5)
      - Graham-Hughes Proposal, 1970-1973 (Box 5)
    - National Council Meetings (Box 5)
      - ASPA National Conference, 1970-1974 (Box 5)
        - 1970 (Box 5)
        - 1974 (Box 5)
        - Los Angeles, 1973 (Box 5)
        - Materials, 1973 (Box 5)
      - ASPA National Council Meetings, 1971; (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - ASPA National Council Minutes, 1972 (Box 5)
      - ASPA National Council and National Office, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - Opinions and Polls (Box 6)
      - Analysis Indiana SOS Regional Campus Totals - Frequencies Interpretation, ca. 1970 (Box 6)
      - Blank Original of Campus Survey, etc., 1970 (Box 6)
      - Bloomington Student Opinion Survey, 1970 (Box 6)
      - Center for the Study of Evaluation, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
      - Codebooks - Indiana SOS, 1970 (Box 6)
      - Crosstab Setup Cards for SOS, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Fort Wayne Student Opinion Survey, 1970 (Box 6)
      - General Instructions for Interviewer, undated (Box 6)
      - Indiana SOS - Questionnaire and Codebook, undated (Box 6)
      - Kokomo Student Opinion Survey, 1970 (Box 6)
      - Library Questions Comparison, 1970 (Box 6)
      - Northwest Student Opinion Survey, 1970 (Box 6)
      - Ohio State University Polls, 1971 (Box 6)
      - South Bend Student Opinion Survey, 1970 (Box 6)
      - IU Southeast, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Student Opinion Polls, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
      - Student Opinion Survey Comparison, 1970 (Box 6)
      - Survey - Miscellaneous, 1970 (Box 6)
      - Vice Presidents' Conference Student Affairs Policy Questionnaire, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Xerox Consulting Service Study, undated (Box 6)
    - Proposals (Box 6)
      - Governmental Studies Program Proposal, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Graduate Studies Program Proposal, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Graham Proposal, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Grant for Human Services Reform, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Health Insurance Proposal, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Marshall Dimock Award, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
      - Policy Internship Program, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
      - Policy Skills Program, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
      - Proposal for the Creation of a National News Publication of Local Government in the United States, undated (Box 6)
      - Sydney Stein Proposal, 1972 (Box 6)
    - School of Public and Environmental Affairs (Box 6)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 6)
      - Alumni, undated (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Degree Program Proposal, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Graduate Program, undated (Box 6)
      - National Association of Schools of Public Affairs and Administration, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Trustee Meeting, 1972 (Box 6)
    - Task Force on Society Goals (Box 7)
      - Task Force on Affiliate Relationships, 1972 (Box 7)
      - APHA Task Force - Health Task Force, 1972 (Box 7)
      - ASPA Task Force, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
      - ASPA Task Force Materials, 1969-1971 (Box 7)
      - ASPA Denver Task Force Materials, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
      - Discussions - Guide Questions, undated (Box 7)
      - The Future of ASPA… Task Force Article, 1970 (Box 7)
      - Task Force on Goals, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
      - Goals Questionnaire, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
      - Goals and Report Preparation, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
      - Goals Task Force Meeting, 1971 (Box 7)
      - ASPA/NASPAA/-OMB/USCSC Joint Task Force, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Meeting, Annual, 1971 (Box 7)
      - Opinion Survey on Society Goals, 1971 (Box 7)
      - Preliminary Recommendations and Implementation Outline, 1971 (Box 7)
      - Preliminary Report, undated (Box 7)
      - Preliminary Report, Revised, 1971 (Box 7)
      - Recommendations, Revised, 1971 (Box 7)
      - Report, Final, 1971 (Box 7)
      - Report, Final Copy as Passed, 1971 (Box 7)
      - Women's Task Force, 1971-1973 (Box 7)
      - Chapter Representative for Women's Task Force on Public Administration, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
      - Task Force on Women's Survey, 1972 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
      - Acknowledgment of Literature Received, 1972 (Box 7)
      - Address File (Box 7)
        - 1972-1973 (Box 7)
        - undated (Box 7)
      - Administrative Committee, 1972 (Box 7)
      - Annual Meeting, 1971 (Box 7)
      - ASPA, 1973 (Box 7)
      - ASPA (Box 7)
        - 1974 (Box 7)
        - 1974-1975 (Box 8)
      - Big 6, 1971-1972 (Box 8)
      - Charles Wise - International Conference for Regional and Branch Campus Institutions, 1972; (legal size) (Box 8)
      - Charlie's Travel, 1971-1972 (Box 8)
      - Chicago, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Conference on Continuing Education and Training in Public Administration, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Conference of Minority Public Administrators, undated (Box 8)
      - Council and Committees, 1975 (Box 8)
      - Fall Council Meeting, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Council Members, 1974-1975 (Box 8)
      - Form Letter to C. W. (Committee Acceptances), 1973 (Box 8)
      - General ASPA Materials, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Handbook for Chapters, 1975 (Box 8)
      - IPA Grant, 1972 (Box 8)
      - Itineraries, 1972 (Box 8)
      - I.U. Personnel, 1969-1970 (Box 8)
      - Linda Correspondence, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Masters - Dr. Williams, undated (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous, 1972-1973 (Box 8)
      - NAPA (Box 8)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 8)
        - 1974-1975 (Box 8)
        - 1975 (Box 8)
        - Spring Meeting, 1974 (Box 8)
      - NASPAA, 1974-1975 (Box 8)
      - National Conference, 1974 (Box 8)
      - National Conference on Public Administration, 1975 (Box 8)
      - National Council, 1973 (Box 8)
      - National Council (Box 8)
        - 1974 (Box 8)
        - 1975 (Box 8)
      - National Council Meeting, 1975 (Box 8)
      - Newsletters (Box 9)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 9)
        - 1975, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Nominating Committee, emph: RESTRICTED (Box 9)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 9)
        - 1974 (Box 9)
      - Poston, Mrs. Ersa H., 1966-ca.1971 (Box 9)